Guide to the Mid-Atlantic Early Manuscripts collection 1974.002
Brooklyn Historical Society
Mid-Atlantic Early Manuscripts collection
1648-1867
Brooklyn Historical Society
Ross, John, 1790-1866
George, King of Great Britain, III
Beecher, Lyman
Toussaint Louverture, 1743-1803
Graham, George, 1772-1830
Franklin, William, 1731-1813
1974.002
0.25 Linear Feet in 21 folders in one half of a manuscript box.
This collection contains correspondence, deeds, indentures, wills, land conveyances, genealogies, and printed materials from the 17th through 19th centuries. The majority of the collection relates to New York and the surrounding states, but some items are from New England or the Mid-Atlantic region. Materials are in English, French, and Dutch. Subjects of note include Native American relations and slavery.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of this collection were the gift of Sylvester Dering, 1890. The source and date of acquisition for the remaining items in the collection are unknown. The collection was formally accessioned in 1974.
Arrangement
Materials have been grouped by subject.
Biographical / Historical
This collection was likely assembled by BHS staff from multiple donations at an unknown date.
Other Finding Aids
Paper finding aid created by Jonathan W. Montgomery in 2005 can be found with the collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, deeds, indentures, wills, land conveyance documents, and printed materials authored by or pertaining to various figures from colonial and early national Long Island, New England, District of Columbia, Tennessee, and Europe. Many documents originate from prominent individuals, such as Lyman Beecher, King George III, John Paul Jones, Robert R. Livingston, William Penn, John Ross, Benjamin Rush, and Noah Webster. Items relate to early colonial and American conflicts, the Louisiana Purchase, slavery, and Native American affairs, particularly those involving the Cherokee Nation. Also included is a letter from General Toussaint Louverture, accompanied by a portrait image.
Indians of North America; Slavery; Legal documents; Deeds; Correspondence; United States |x History |y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Wills; Tennessee; London (England); Paris (France); United States |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783; New Jersey; Pennsylvania; District of Columbia; South Carolina; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Connecticut; Massachusetts; Virginia; United States |x History |y 1783-1865; New York (State); Louisiana Purchase; United States |x Politics and government; Genealogy; Debt; Mattituck (N.Y.) -- New York (State); Elections |z New York (State); Census; Bills of exchange; Articles of apprenticeship; Shipping records; Jamaica (New York, N.Y.); Dutchess County (N.Y.); Oyster Bay (N.Y.); Sermons; Suffolk County (N.Y.); Lake Champlain, Battle of, N.Y., 1814; Gerritsen family; Jackson, Andrew; Uncass, Sachem of the Munheags; Philip, Sachem of the Wampanoags, -1676; Custis, John Parke, 1754-1781; Williams, Ann; Jefferson, Thomas; Franklin, Benjamin; Wright, Anthony; Crabb, Alice; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.. Presbytery of Long Island; Madison, James, 1751-1836; Cherokee; Corchaug; Munheag
- Letter from Dr. Benjamin Rush to Dr. John Cowan, 1795 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 1)
- Revolutionary War correspondence, poetry, and military documents, 1779-1782 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence of General Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, 1818 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 3)
- Long Island legal documents, correspondence, genealogy, and bills, 1636-1761 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bond of debt owed by Christopher Rodgers, 1765 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 5)
- Memorandum of S. Hambleton and correspondence of Henry G. Morton, 1820-1854 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence concerning relations between the U.S. government and the Cherokee Nation, 1817-1835 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 7)
- Connecticut legal documents, Native American relations, and correspondence, 1648-1859 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 8)
- Suffolk County, LI, election records, resolution of the Continental Congress, and order for a census, 1776 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 9)
- Land, military, and estate documents of miscellaneous colonial figures, including records of slave ownership, 1681-1797 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 10)
- Massachusetts correspondence and donation receipts, 1669-1867 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 11)
- Ann Williams correspondence regarding debts, 1859-1861 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Colonial and early national correspondence, 1722-1885 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 13)
- New Jersey official correspondence and letters of indenture, 1769-1830 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 14)
- New York census acts and correspondence, 1713-1715 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 15)
- Dutchess County colonial bills of sale and deeds, including records of slave ownership, 1751-1766 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 16)
- Long Island wills, Lyman Beecher correspondence, and Church documents, 1673-1861 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence of Adolph Philipse and Philip Hicks, and records of the Port of New York, 1728-1788 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 18)
- Jamaica, LI, land deeds, 1713-1786 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 19)
- Account of the Battle of Lake Champlain, 1814 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letter from Jacobus Bleecker to his parents, 1745 (Box 1974.002 Box 1, Folder 21)